Guide to the Physicians for Social Responsibility, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1960s-2006 AIS.2005.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Physicians for Social Responsibility, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1960-2006
1971-2004
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Physicians for Social Responsibility (U.S.). Pittsburgh Chapter
AIS.2005.02
4.75 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Physicians for Social Responsibility (PSR) is a non-profit organization dedicated to educating the public about the medical hazards of nuclear weapons and advocating nuclear disarmament. These records reflect the work done by PSR Pittsburgh from its founding in 1971 to 2006. The majority of the records cover the group's efforts, during the 1980s, to promote bans on nuclear testing, reduction and eventual abolition of nuclear weapons, and amicable relations between the United States and the Soviet Union. Most material in this collection is in the form of minutes, correspondence, information about nuclear weapons, and records from public events.
History
Physicians for Social Responsibility (PSR) is a non-profit organization dedicated to advocating nuclear disarmament and educating the public about the medical hazards of nuclear weapons. The group began in the early 1960s in response to atom bomb testing. PSR was instrumental in the signing of the Partial Test Ban Treaty in 1963 and has worked for the signing of the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty since then. The national organization is based in Washington, D.C., and maintains a website at http://www.psr.org.
In 1971, a group of physicians from the Pittsburgh area met to form a group dedicated to important current social issues, including nuclear weapons and the Vietnam War, and organized themselves as PSR Pittsburgh, the chapter of PSR representing western Pennsylvania.
PSR is the United States affiliate of International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War (IPPNW), which was founded in 1980 and was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1985. Other groups which have worked with PSR at national and local levels include Peace Links, the Union of Concerned Scientists, Educators for Social Responsibility, Faculty for Social Responsibility, and the Thomas Merton Center. In 1984 PSR Pittsburgh and the Pittsburgh chapter of Pennsylvania Peace Links joined with other groups to form the Pittsburgh Coalition to Prevent Nuclear War.
Scope and Content Notes
These records come from files kept by Dr. Jack Paradise, a pediatrics professor at the University of Pittsburgh, who has participated actively in PSR Pittsburgh since its founding, serving intermittently in leadership offices throughout the 1980s and 1990s. Files from the 1970s show the beginning steps to organize local physicians into what became PSR Pittsburgh, the group's opposition to the Vietnam War, and their attempts to work for the benefit of Chilean health workers under the Pinochet regime.
PSR Pittsburgh was especially active in the early to mid-1980s, organizing public events to raise public awareness of the dangers of nuclear weapons, call for nuclear disarmament, and promote amicable relations between the United States and the Soviet Union. The bulk of the records in this collection date from that time, but there is also some documentation relating to other issues, including the Iraq war begun in 2003.
In October 2009, Dr. Jack Paradise donated additional materials relating to the organization. Included were files from the national chapter of Physicians for Social Responsibility in the 1960s and additional files on the "In Concert for Peace" event. The new material has been added at the end of each existing series. Further scope notes are found after each series title.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in three series. Series I contains general minutes and correspondence; Series II holds a great deal of information about nuclear weapons gathered from various sources; and Series III shows the activities that PSR Pittsburgh organized in pursuit of its mission. The three series are named as follows:
Series I. Administrative Files
Series II. Subject Files
Series III. Outreach Activities
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Accruals
Additional material received in June 2006 and October 2009.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jack Paradise in May 2005.
Previous Citation
Physicians for Social Responsibility, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1971-2004, AIS.2005.02, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Pennsylvania Peace Links Records, 1981-2004, AIS.2004.09, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Pittsburgh Peace Institute Records, 1984-1997, AIS.1998.01, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Thomas Merton Center Records, 1971-2004, AIS.1982.19, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Separated Material
Newsletters, including the IPPNW Report and the PSR Monitor, have been cataloged in the University Library System, along with other publications donated with the collection.
Peace movements -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies, etc.; Antinuclear movement -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Physicians -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Political activity; Social action; Associations; Nuclear disarmament; Paradise, Jack; Educators for Social Responsibility (U.S.); Faculty for Social Responsibility (U.S.); International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War; Lown, Bernard; Peace Links; Pennsylvania Peace Links; Physicians for Social Responsibility (U.S.). Pittsburgh Chapter; Pittsburgh Coalition to Prevent Nuclear War (Pa.); Rush, Molly; Thomas Merton Center (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Union of Concerned Scientists
- Administrative Files, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series holds correspondence, minutes, lists of members and financial information. Minutes from meetings of the general membership and various committees are arranged in rough chronological order and indicate the planning processes behind group activities. Filed with the minutes are by-laws, drafts of statements, annual reports of the national organization, newsletters, articles, and other documents discussed in the meetings. A series of meetings from 1984 to 1988 with the Pittsburgh Coalition to Prevent Nuclear War is also represented in the minutes, in Folder 5 of Box 1. Recently added material can be found under the section "New Material Added."
  - Minutes, 1971-2004, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Correspondence, 1970-2003 (Box 1, Folder 6-13)
  - Tax Exemption, By-laws, General Information, 1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Membership, Recruitment (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Advisory Board Member Packet (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Foundation Money for Grants (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - New Material Added, 2009
    - Physicians for Social Responsibility National Organization, 1960s, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Draft of Joint Statement by Physicians of Western Pennsylvania and the USSR regarding Nuclear Testing, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Membership lists and information, 1987, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Subject Files, II.
  Most of the files in this series were kept for use in public education and outreach programs. They are drawn from diverse published sources and contain information about the dangers of nuclear war, groups and individuals allied with PSR, and the articulation of opposing viewpoints. Some material from IPPNW is found in this series, including reports of proceedings from annual conferences and articles about that group's reception of the Nobel Peace Prize in 1985. The files of news clippings include letters to the editors of newspapers written by members of PSR Pittsburgh. See Box 2, Folder 26 for information about various organizations allied with PSR, including Educators for Social Responsibility, Faculty for Social Responsibility, and the Thomas Merton Center. Recently added material can be found under the section "New Material Added."
  - Articles and Clippings (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Articles and Clippings (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - B-1 Bomber (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bibliographies, Brochures, Educational Materials (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Caldicott, Dr. Helen (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Children (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Comprehensive Test Ban (CTB) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - CTB Coordinating Committee (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Department of Defense (DOD) Civilian-Military Contingency Hospitalization System (CMCHS) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War (IPPNW) (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
  - Iraq (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Medical, Health Consequences of Nuclear War (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Methodist Bishops (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Nobel Peace Prize, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Nuclear Attack Effects on Pittsburgh (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Nuclear Winter (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Peace Academy (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Peace Links (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Pittsburgh Coalition to Prevent Nuclear War (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - People Reaching Out for Peace (PRO Peace) March (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Professionals' Coalition for Nuclear Arms Control (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Related Organizations (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Star Wars (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - New Material Added, 2009
    - Business Executives for Nuclear Arms Control, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Computer Professionals for Social Responsibility, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Educators for Social Responsibility, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Faculty for Social Responsibility, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Nurses Alliance for the Prevention of Nuclear War, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 20-20 Vision National Project, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Outreach Activities, III.
  PSR coordinated and participated in many events to draw public attention to the dangers of nuclear war and nuclear energy, and to encourage civic participation in political processes aimed towards nuclear disarmament. Such events included conferences and symposia, press conferences, petitions and grassroots campaigns, and visits of American and Soviet physicians. In collaboration with Pennsylvania Peace Links and Musicians against Nuclear Arms (MANA), PSR Pittsburgh organized "In Concert for Peace," a performance of classical music which was held on May 1, 1984. In that same year, the newly-formed Pittsburgh Coalition to Prevent Nuclear War organized the "Series on Survival," a series of symposia held at various locations throughout Pittsburgh. These two events in particular are amply documented in this series. Recently added material, mostly relating to the In Concert for Peace can be found under the section "New Material Added."
  - Abolition 2000 Campaign (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Billboard (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - City Council Hearing 3/30/82 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Citizen's Forum on Nuclear Arms Control, October 16, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Code Blue --Washington (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Concert for Humanity, April 17, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Conference Brochures (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Conference Planning (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Event Notices (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - GSPH Symposium (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - In Concert for Peace, May 1, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6-10)
  - Lown, Dr. Bernard, Pittsburgh Visit (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - National Meetings (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Pacem in Terris IV, Dec 2-4, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Peace Garden of Riverfront Park (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Petition to President and Congress, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Petition, Reply from George Bush, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Pittsburgh Pediatric Society Meeting (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Presentation, Unspecified, Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Press Conference Planning (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Press Conference: Ethics for Lunch (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Press Contacts and Releases (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - New York Times Advertisement, March 2, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper Advertisement: Vietnam and Kent State, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Planning for Peace and Prosperity Conference, April 4-5, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Public Relations Recommendations Report, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Recruiting Materials (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Roots, Fears and Realities of Nuclear War Symposium, May 21, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Series on Survival - Meeting Rooms, October-November 1984 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Series on Survival - Miscellaneous, October-November 1984 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Series on Survival - Redlener, Dr. Irwin, October-November 1984 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Series on Survival - Rush, Molly, October-November 1984 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Series on Survival - Thomas, L., October-November 1984 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Soviet Physicians' Visits (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Specter, Senator Arlen: Letter and Response, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Speeches, Talks (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Slides (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Various Outreach Materials (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - New Material Added, 2009
    - College outreach, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Concert for Humanity, concerts in additional cities, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - The Day After, psychological impact of film, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - In Concert for Peace address cards of attendees, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - In Concert for Peace art committee, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - In Concert for Peace assorted task lists, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - In Concert for Peace committee agendas and assignments, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - In Concert for Peace correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - In Concert for Peace financial information, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - In Concert for Peace information for ticket sales, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - In Concert for Peace marketing, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - In Concert for Peace program, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - In Concert for Peace Shigeko Sasamori appearance, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - In Concert for Peace statement of purpose, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - In Concert for Peace stationery, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - In Concert for Peace ticket advertisement, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Point Park College channel 21 interview of Bernard Lown, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Point Park College outreach, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Pot luck dinner in honor of Soviet physicians' visit, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - October series seminar planning, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 14)